It's eater.
Where did she come from?
I don't know. I heard
someone running down.
- I thought it was the killer.
- No. it's not.
It doesn't mean we're safe.
We don't know who she is.
We could ask her.
- It's just an idea.
- It's not your job to have ideas.
What do we do?
Watch her and check our weapons.
Okay.
I can't believe you. Rick.
what were you thinking?
I had it under control.
Why would you do that?
- I was ju... I...
- spit it out!
Because she was gonna die.
Yeah. that was the point. Rick.
I cut the rope.
- Well. you...
- she was headed to it.
You could've told me.
What is that?
- Where is she?
- She went back in.
Don't go!
Do I look bad?
- No. no. no. I...
- is that
I just... I thought maybe
you'd look different.
Is that the killer?
Hey. Wait. did I hurt you? Are you okay?
- Yes! No! Kinda.
- No? Okay. Come on.
- We have to kill him.
- I'm sorry.
It's not your fault.
It's okay.
Okay.
Why didn't you do it?
But he can get us into the vault.
- Shit.
- He's still breathing.
- I'll finish it.
- No. no. no.
He can't get us food if he's dead.
We have to get out of here.
Come on.
Get the ax. And then
tell us if she's coming up.
Hey. what did he say?
I knew it. He didn't give you the code.
- No. it was ju...
- I told you to get the ax.
She came out of the water.
She's coming up the stairs.
She's gonna see the blood. Fuck!
No. I added blood.
You added blood?
Yeah. My own. To lead her away.
You know. even if she
finds us. we could use her.
Maybe if she's in danger.
he can give us the code.
No. it's not worth the risk.
If she gets too close. we scare her off.
And then we kill him.
like we said we would.
and leave his body so she
knows to stay the fuck away.
- What if we try something else? What if...
- no one wants to hear your ideas.
All right?
Just keep a lookout and let
us know if she's coming or not.
Audrey. wait.
Stop!
Hey!
I already put one arrow in your shoulder.
One more move and this one
goes straight into your heart.
Just listen. The man you took
has something that belongs to me.
I just want it back. That's all.
We told you. he's dead.
If he was dead. you
would've put his body there
and you would've shot
me as soon as I got close.
Look. we can trade.
You set him free. and I'll let her go.
We don't give a shit about her.
I'm gonna leave. I need my stuff.
So I need to see him. I need
to talk to him. He has my stu
you can talk to him if you
get us the food from his vault.
- I don't know the code.
- Figure it out.
What the fuck are you doing?
What. are you just gonna
let her out of our sight?
I'll go with her.
Fine. Good.
This is your fault anyway.
If you try anything. we'll know.
I just fed my baby
and she won't cry
again until she's hungry.
If you don't get into the vault
by the next time she cries...
Okay.
We'll kill your friend.
We think we're the chosen ones...
But we're just one of many.
The founders didn't build a single silo.
They built 50.
Technically. 51.
Why?
Good question.
I don't know.
Could Juliette have
made it to another silo?
She did. But then the images
from her helmet cut out.
So she could still be alive?
Unlikely.
That silo is no longer functional.
All it heads and their shadows
know about the other silos.
That is not what Quinn
would need to put in code.
Keep going.
The day I found the book. I
knew I was supposed to destroy it.
But there was something
inside me. it wouldn't let go.
Why is it illegal for us to have this?
I don't know.
It's not right. Paul.
Whatever happened. this was our world.
We deserve to know where we came
from. no matter what the pact says.
I know that makes you uncomfortable...
But I also know it's true.
You know. you can't just
keep trying random numbers.
- You only get three tries per day...
- I know.
Look. if you know something that
actually would help me. then come with me.
If not. just wait.
Okay? It's not like I can sneak
out some other way. right?
- You said you were going outside?
- Yeah. I've tried but every time I
can I go with you?
No. there's one suit.
And if I don't get
into the vault. well. I'm
let me help.
You heard me. right? One suit.
Okay. let's go.
After holston died. they came to
me about taking over as sheriff.
I thought they saw a leader in me.
Now I know that wasn't it.
What they really saw was someone
they could count on to fall in line.
to not ask questions.
But they misjudged me.
I have a lot of questions
and I am not willing to
leave them unanswered.
Not anymore.
It was Juliette.
She was the one who
made me open my eyes.
start to see it's time.
The lies have to stop.
Well. that was a good speech.
But. what exactly can you do for us?
You asked for my help.
I didn't realize there was
nothing you could actually do.
We have another traitor we have to find.
Someone gave up the supply raid.
How can he help with that? He
doesn't know people down here.
He knows people up top.
Any way the other deputies
would line up with us?
- I don't know.
- Why not?
That's right. because all communication
was severed. thanks to you.
- Shirl.
- Am I wrong?
What was I supposed to do?
Maybe not tell Bernard over the radio
that you were gonna launch an
investigation into him and sims.
I'm sorry.
It's just. we can't do this alone.
But we don't know if
anyone's on our side.
There is one person.
The woman who helped us get down.
Yeah. I was thinking of her.
But I don't see how we could contact her.
Who are you talking about?
Camille sims.
You read?
Can you read?
- Yeah.
- Okay. great.
Can you look for anything that
says "Russell" or "head of it" on it?
If the code was just written
down. someone would've found it.
Yeah. I don't know
what else to do right now.
So if you could help me
find anything. that'll be great.
Yeah.
The people in the other room
that died. did you see them?
Yeah.
Tess was Rick's mom and
chase was Audrey's dad.
and they got together after the
other parents died and had Benny.
When my mom got sick.
she brought me to them.
She asked if they'd take me in.
And they did. when she died.
But I was kinda just... I was
just another mouth to feed.
That's why they wanted
to get into the vault.
That's why they died.
We were hungry.
The others. they blame me.
That's why they call me eater.
That's all I am to them.
Look. I understand.
More than you know.
- Okay? Just right now. I need...
- I know. We'll look for the code.
I just wanted to tell you.
Hey. what about this?
- This...
- that's his apartment.
- It's a different address.
- Is it something?
We will see.
Here's what you gotta know.
Okay? That page
that your husband has?
That's nothing.
I mean. you have no idea
what they're not telling us.
What are they not telling us?
You around a computer
when Nichols was caught?
No.
Well. if you had been. you'd have seen.
You'd know what I'm talking about.
You'd also be in a small
room with a bag over your head.
Thanks.
You remember when
the sheriff's wife cleaned?
What she said before she
said she wanted to go out?
"The display is a lie."
Exactly.
That page you saw?
Maybe that's not just
the way things were.
Maybe
maybe that's the way things are.
Hey. have you seen mayor Holland?
No.
Okay. well. I need to find him. like. now.
- He's unreachable.
- What is that supposed to mean?
It means you have to wait.
Okay. listen. You don't
understand. all right?
Look. the life of the silo depends
on me finding him right now.
You don't understand.
Your life depends on
you letting go of my arm.
I have orders not to
disturb him until this evening.
Walk.
- What do you want?
- Missed you at breakfast.
Wasn't hungry.
Shirl said that you weren't feeling good.
That's bullshit.
What she said was. "walk
can't leave her workshop again."
Ever since I got back. I
can't go near that door.
I can't even think about it without
my heart jumping into my throat.
I was wrong to think I
could get over it. I was stupid.
It wasn't stupid.
- Just takes time.
- Yeah. Well. there isn't any.
They've got my wife.
First time I lost her.
that's when this all started.
It's not gonna go away.
Not if I don't get her back.
Walk. look at me.
Look at me.
You're gonna get her back.
How do you know?
'Cause you missed
something at breakfast.
We have the sheriff now.
He's with us.
We're gonna take control of the silo.
And the first thing we're gonna do
is free mclain.
I just wanted you to
know that we have a plan.
Get some rest.
You heard everything I did.
How do I know. when you
got me shackled to this room?
Mom.
Lukas. what's wrong?
- Where have you been? Are you okay?
- Nothing's wrong. mom.
All I got was a note saying my son had
been sentenced to five years in the mines.
Well. they released me.
All right. look. I can't
explain all of that
- you've been free for how long?
- Not long. I couldn't get away.
- To tell me you're safe?
- Just... mom. I need you to take this.
Hide it somewhere no
one can find it. okay?
No. I won't. I thought I'd lost you.
- You're putting your life at risk again?
- You don't understand.
You were always this
way. even as a little boy.
- I don't have a choice.
- There's peace in the unknown. Lukas.
I wish you could find it. but
you're driven to solve things
even when they can't be solved.
And now it's led you here. to whatever
no. what's led me
here is being a coward.
Sheriff Nichols came to me for help
and I told her I couldn't give it to her
because I was the only
one taking care of my mother.
- What? But you don't...
- I lied.
I lied to her. mom. to get
out of doing the right thing.
And I didn't help her.
I didn't report her either. I just...
Did nothing.
I'm not gonna make
that same mistake again.
- Okay?
- Yeah.
Hey.
Thank you.
Your Russell guy had a kid.
Hey. what do you eat in your silo?
It changes.
Depends on what they
have in the cafeteria.
So you never had to eat a rat?
No.
What is it?
Nothing.
So you said chase and Tess.
they were trying to get into the vault.
Yeah. but they never found the code.
They gave up looking for it.
They just kept trying new numbers.
I don't know how they kept track.
What did you say?
I do.
- Shit.
- What?
I drew that. but I didn't
know that the numbers were
chase and Tess wrote
these. I know their handwriting.
So they got in. right?
Otherwise. he wouldn't have killed them.
So it would have been here.
which I erased. That's great.
Anyway. I think I can figure
it out with what I've got here.
One. two. three. four.
five. six. seven. eight...
Fifteen. 16. 17.
So. nine. 29. 30. 31.
32. 33. 34. 35. 36. 37.
Thirty-seven. 38.
One. two. three. four.
One. two.
Zero. three.
Why do these all have two names?
Bobby Parsons. Lynn
Montgomery. Emily ames.
The first is your first name and
the second one's called your last.
Do you have one? A last name.
Yeah. Nichols.
My mom only gave me one.
Doesn't matter anymore.
The baby will wake up soon.
Okay. could you bring me a slate please?
Eight. nine.
- Nobody gets any further.
- The mayor sent me.
You know. I'm his shadow.
I have authorization to cross. so...
Unless you wanna be reported
for obstructing my movement
it's not safe down there.
Are you sure you wanna go?
I'm sure.
Make it quick.
Hey! Grab him! Come here!
- Okay. all right.
- All right. let's go.
Look. I need to get to the bottom.
They let this one through.
- Who are you?
- I'm Lukas Kyle.
What would someone from it.
with a blue ID no less. be
doing in the down deep?
Who sent you?
No one. I came on my own.
- Take him back.
- No. hey. listen.
You think I would be coming
down here in the middle of all of this
if I didn't have to?
Fuck. I am trying to save the silo.
If Mr. Blue ID continues to be an
asshole. pitch him over the side.
Fuck. stop!
Just... wait. I knew Juliette Nichols.
Like hell you did.
Her boyfriend's name was George.
As the senior members
of your department.
I wanted to brief you on
the rebels' latest assault.
which I'm sure you're aware of.
We are. sir.
Their intention was to
steal gunpowder from supply
and use it to blast open the silo door.
We were able to stop their reckless plan.
a plan we've since realized
was put into motion by Paul billings.
How do we know that?
The rebels in custody all
identified him as responsible.
As such. we've decided
to strip billings of his badge
and leave the post
vacant until further notice.
One last thing.
all deputies and their support staff
are being assigned to
the cafeteria on this level.
We need to convert it into
a temporary holding cell.
You want us to build a jail?
You told us that we wouldn't have
to do anything related to the rebellion.
Unfortunately.
circumstances have changed.
Shit.
- There's still one left.
- Yeah. I know.
But if I get it wrong. then
we're locked out for 24 hours...
And solo will fucking die.
- So...
- That's his name? Solo?
- Why?
- I don't know.
Is it his first or second name?
No. it's just not his name at all.
That's solo.
That's not you.
That is the actual it shadow.
I don't know who you are.
I am the it shadow.
Do you understand?
Do not say those words
to me! Don't you ever!
Do you understand? I am solo.
I am the it shadow!
He's not who he says he is.
She used to sit next to me.
She said that her name
meant blue or something.
Solo? This is a level b classroom?
So she would've been 11 or
12 when the rebellion started.
So. how were you sitting next to her?
Well. I didn't say that
this belonged to her.
It's just that it reminded me of her.
The rebellion...
How old were you when that happened?
I wasn't born yet.
My mom didn't even remember.
She was just a baby then.
Fuck.
He was just a kid.
That was solo's classroom.
Conroy.
That's Russell's last name.
In the apartment. The lunch box.
Hey.
That's him.
If you're the one in charge.
I need you to let me go.
How did you know Jules?
We used to talk in the cafeteria.
when she was leaving work. okay?
Then you didn't really know her.
I know that she was
searching for the truth.
So am I.
That's what brought me down here.
Sounds like something your
boss would tell you to say.
Hey. wait. I think
Juliette could still be alive.
Where?
I'll tell you.
But only if you take
me where I need to go.
I've got no idea who it could be.
Bernard got a tip-off on
the raid from someone.
Another listener?
Could be.
How'd they get a message to Bernard?
There's no computers. no porters.
Maybe they passed a piece
of paper to one of the raiders.
- I mean. that's what you did.
- Yeah. but I have no idea
if that message got where I want it to go.
Sheriff. they're asking
for you at the barricade.
Someone to see you.
Looks like your message got through.
You want us to come with
you? A show of strength?
Better if it's just me.
Getting a message
through the barricade.
What? What is it?
I know who betrayed us.
- Wa... hey. You get in?
- No.
- Hey. you need to let me talk to him.
- No. that wasn't the deal.
Okay.
Look. your parents. they
figured out the code. right?
I've narrowed it down
to six combinations.
I get three chances a day.
I've tried two. so the
only way I can get in
- is if you let me talk to him.
- No. you don't get to see him.
If you let her kill him.
you'll never get in.
- You need to open the vault!
- No. I don't.
I don't need to. I could just leave. right?
I don't need to get into
the fucking vault. You do.
- You need to get int...
- wait. wait.
That's my mom's.
Where did you get that?
Her talking to him is the best shot
we have at getting into the vault.
Hey.
Hey. are you okay?
Shit.
- I failed.
- What?
No. No... you didn't
- he told me...
- What do you mean?
Not to let anyone in the vault.
Well. I didn't get in. No
one's been in the vault.
Then what are you doing here?
Look. I understand how
important it is to protect the vault.
I do.
I get it.
I promise you. if you give me the code
- I won't. I...
- no. please. Just listen.
I'll go in. I'll get food.
That's all they want.
I could... I want to go back to my silo.
No. Just... you might as well let
them come in here and kill me now.
No. just think about it please.
- Russell chose me to be his shadow.
- No.
I am the only one left
to keep the vault safe.
You were never his shadow.
- I swore an oath.
- No.
But you weren't his shadow.
You were his son.
Benny. I told you to use the ladder.
I will. Next time.
I'll be right back.
Are you gonna kill him now?
Hey. do you remember?
I've never seen this before.
- I know you don't want to try but I...
- get out!
- Hey. no. No. just wait.
- Just
- fine.
- Stop. please.
I have more arrows.
Audrey. wait.
You're taking their side?
I wanna hear what he has to say.
Just put it down.
Okay. okay.
Tell us how you killed our parents.
- What happened?
- He asked me to do one thing
- and I failed.
- What do you mean you failed?
They got in. They got the
right code and they got in.
And I was right there. I was
right there and I did nothing.
Even after they came
in. I didn't wake up.
- I did...
- you were asleep?
I didn't... I did... I.
I didn't wake up until...
It's okay. Until what? What?
It was very loud.
What was loud?
I'm so fucking stupid. I
left the gun by the door.
Did they shoot you
while you were asleep?
- Is that what happened?
- You can't believe him.
- Rick.
- Then what?
He killed our parents.
- I didn't want to.
- But you did!
They got inside the food vault.
So.
I broke off the inside handle
of the door and I shut it.
and they couldn't get
out 'cause it was sealed.
So they ran out of air?
It doesn't matter how he did it.
He killed them and he's
lying about them shooting him.
Do you have a scar?
Yeah? I know you
don't want to show them
but they need to know
you're telling the truth.
- I'm not lying.
- Can I just
- yeah?
- Yeah.
Okay.
Are you gonna give us the code or not?
Fine.
How about this?
We'll figure it out
eventually ourselves. right?
So we don't need him.
One less eater.
Your name's Jimmy Conroy.
- Move. I said move!
- And you were 12 when the rebellion
you were 12... stop!
Stop. please. Just listen.
He was 12. okay. when the
rebellion happened. Twelve.
He wasn't old enough to be able
to be responsible for all of this.
You were 12.
Jimmy was a coward.
- No.
- Jimmy hid behind a door...
Open the damn door. Jimmy!
While the sheriff held a
gun to his father's head.
All he had to do was open
the door and he didn't. So
dad.
Does that sound like
the son of a hero to you?
Russell would've been
ashamed to have a son like that.
No. you're wrong. He
would've been so proud
'cause you did what he asked you to do.
"Don't open the door.
Don't let anyone in."
- That's what he said to you. right?
- Yeah.
Yeah. do you know why he said that?
'Cause he wanted to save the vault.
Because he wanted to save the silo.
No. No. Jimmy.
He wanted to save you.
He wanted you to live.
Come... just like their
parents wanted them to live.
That's why your father
was protecting you.
Just like they want
their child to live. Okay?
They have a kid?
They have a baby.
A baby.
- It's okay.
- Rick.
- I need to do it.
It's okay.
Okay.
Yeah?
- Yeah. Okay.
- Okay.
You got my message?
No. Paul. I just decided to
walk down a hundred levels.
Where's the relic?
We need privacy.
On the stairs. in the
middle of a rebellion?
So it's true.
You really have crossed the line.
Gone over to the other side.
I didn't go anywhere.
The line moved.
Let me see it.
It's not safe to open here.
You made me come all this way
'cause I'm the only one you could trust.
- Come on. we both know that's a lie.
- You're right.
I wanted to see your wife.
But all I had for bait was
this relic. so it had to be you.
She helped two rebels escape
capture when they were on the run.
which makes me wonder if
maybe some of us care more
about the safety of the
silo than anything else.
When you see this...
You'll understand why I don't
have any choice but to trust you.
To do what?
I haven't been down this far in years.
Jules hinted this is where
she came with George.
You were right. you know. I.
I didn't really know her.
We only talked a few times
and... I never met anyone like her.
There isn't anyone like her.
Yeah.
I thought she was amazing.
So amazing that I tried to kiss her.
And you're still alive?
You're lucky.
I didn't know about George.
Not until later.
I just
I wish I would've done
something more to help her.
We all do.
Yeah.
I've been coming down here for years.
I've never heard anything about a tunnel.
You're sure it's down there?
Yeah. that's what I was told.
Then you were lied to.
The only thing at the bottom is water.
I don't think it's that deep.
Right? Think about it.
This whole space should be
filled with water. but it's not.
So. what?
You're saying there's pumps down there
that mechanical doesn't know about?
There have to be.
You willing to bet your life on that?
Yes.
Yeah. I'm coming.
Since when do you have to knock?
I thought you'd want to know.
I figured out who the traitor is.
It's Teddy's mom.
I saw her yesterday
before the raid on supply.
She was at the barricade.
I think she was just afraid...
That Teddy would be killed.
Did you talk to her?
Not yet.
Can't punish her.
Not for trying to protect her son.
But we're in a jam now. walk.
What we're doing. it's not working.
We gotta change the game.
Why are you telling me?
I couldn't find shirl and
needed someone to run it by.
I'm all ears.
You know the rest of the
gunpowder we took from supply?
We're gonna use it.
You just... you know
this is
it's a boat I've been working on.
It's a sailboat.
You know. I was gonna
heat up some food.
but I think maybe we should
start with something else.
Ice cream.
- Wait. wait.
- No. it's okay. You can go in.
This is it.
Yeah. let's...
Just leave
hey.
Okay. It's okay.
They're drums. You play 'em.
Yeah.
- Like that?
- Yep.
Wow.
Birds.
Hey. you guys wanna hear some music?
What's that?
It's music. It.
I actually think it's
better than ice cream.
I kept it safe.
Thanks.
This isn't the only suit though.
There's one you didn't
tell me about. right?
The head of it gets a suit. in
case the air lock is breached
and they need to safely
get back to the vault.
- What is it?
- Nothing.
I'm sorry that I didn't tell you about it.
That's fine. I almost drowned and...
Got shot with an arrow.
I don't understand that.
If you found a suit. why
didn't you just leave?
You ready?
Yeah.
You okay?
- Wait.
- What?
Tell me what happened to Jules.
In case I die?
Well. yeah.
Right.
Right. There was a camera
in her cleaning helmet.
And when it stopped
working. she was still alive.
- What?
- Yeah.
Did you see her?
No. it's what I was told.
Does that mean she's still out there?
I don't know. I... if I
knew. I would tell you.
But I hope so.
Right. Wish me luck.
You're gonna need it.
'Cause you're on your own.
Great.
Do you think it's real?
I don't know.
- It's time for us to pick a side.
- You think they'll win?
They might. if you do
what Paul billings asked.
Rob. if they do win. they'll
need someone to run the silo.
That could be you.
This is what we need to do.
For Anthony.
I can't do it.
They see me as the enemy.
Okay.
Okay. I'll do it.
There is something else I can do.
Bernard has a key.
Number 18 on it.
And when things go sideways.
it lights up and buzzes.
and he disappears.
It happened when we got word
mayor jahns picked Nichols to be sheriff.
He took off. I followed him.
He used the key to go through
the door into the server room.
When he returned. he told
me he had to become mayor.
What's in the server room?
Besides servers.
I don't know.
The only person with
access is the head of it
or whoever has the key.
Lukas Kyle.
Why are you here?
I was given instructions.
By whom?
Salvador Quinn.
Before you. only three
people have reached this door:
Salvador Quinn. Mary
meadows. and George Wilkins.
I did not speak with Wilkins.
Quinn and meadows were both given
the same directive you will now receive.
If you speak to anyone
about this conversation
or what you have seen down here.
we will have no choice
but to initiate the safeguard.
Do you know what the
safeguard is. Mr. Kyle?
I do.